Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
(Noble Lady Sourire)
Is the name tag for Noble Lady Sourire ready?
Just finished. Shall we put it in tonight?
His Majesty didn't give an edict.
Let's keep it here.
Lady Sourire is His Majesty's new favorite.
I'm sure her name tag will be used quite a bit.
The red candles haven't been burning for nothing.
The crabapple tree has finally blossomed.
His Majesty's visits have brought
more yang energy to balance the yin of our palace.
Peace to Lady Sourire.
Congratulations, My Lady.
His Majesty grants you a bath at the Hot Spring Palace.
Madam Jinxi is requested to go with you.
I thank His Majesty.
Madam Jinxi, please help My Lady get ready for the trip.
The carriage will be waiting outside the palace gate after lunch.
Yes, I will get everything ready for My Lady.
Then I will take my leave, My Lady.
There's also a lot of work to do at the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
Where is the Hot Spring Palace?
Why do you need a carriage?
It's an imperial palace in Changping [outside of Beijing].
His Majesty probably wants a getaway
from the rules and crowds in the palace.
My Lady has a weak constitution.
The hot springs will nourish her health.
Your Majesty.
Is everything ready? When will His Majesty depart?
We will leave after lunch.
Su Peisheng said Lady Sourire was granted
a bath in the Hot Spring Palace.
Autumn,
report to His Majesty that I'm not feeling well today.
I won't be able to accompany him.
Yes.
Your Majesty...
Your Majesty will be using the Gold Phoenix Springs
while Lady Sourire will use the Blue Phoenix Pool.
She won't disturb Your Majesty.
His Majesty is in a good mood today.
Why don't I let his wish be fulfilled?
How virtuous Your Majesty is.
I can't imagine what would happen
if Consort Fleur were going with her.
Is Your Majesty imitating the Emperor Cheng of Han?
[who liked to watch his concubines bathe]
I dare not be Zhao Hede.
[Emperor Cheng's most favored consort]
How dare you compare me to Emperor Cheng of Han?
[Emperor Cheng was an epic playboy]
Emperor Cheng could only gaze in awe at Your Majesty's sagacity.
You flatter me, but I'm pleased to hear it.
But you're in the harem.
How can you tell that I'm a sagacious emperor?
You can't comment on the state affairs.
I know nothing about the affairs at court.
But I know one thing:
Because Your Majesty rules all under Heaven,
the beauty of your concubines surpasses that of Emperor Cheng's,
and more importantly, their virtues go beyond Ban Jieyu's.
[Emperor Cheng's most virtuous consort]
Emperor Cheng was far less blessed than Your Majesty.
My Noble Lady Sourire has a sharp wit and a quick tongue.
She far exceeds Emperor Cheng's consorts Feiyan and Hede.
I am more fortunate than Emperor Cheng.
Are you scared?
Not, Your Majesty.
You're too scared to even look at me.
Concubines are always afraid
when they serve in bed for the first time.
I'm not feeling scared.
I'm just a concubine to Your Majesty,
but I see you as my husband.
And this is my wedding night.
That's why I'm nervous.
Don't be.
The etiquette instructor must have told you what to do.
I feel nervous
because I was instructed on how to serve an emperor.
I did not learn how I should serve my husband.
I meant no offense to Your Majesty.
All my concubines served me in fear and awe.
Even the Empress is meticulously careful.
No one has ever said such a thing to me.
If you see me as your husband,
you don't need to be overly cautious with your husband.
Your Majesty's back has been hurting since morning.
Now that Your Highness has taken the medicine,
you should rest early.
She has served His Majesty finally.
It's been a long time. That's not a big deal.
Her promotion was an exception
and His Majesty visited her every two days.
Now she's granted a stay at the Hot Spring Palace.
No other concubine went.
Is she the next Noble Consort Yang?
[most beloved consort of Emperor Xuanzong of Tang]
In the end, Noble Consort Yang had a tragic death at Mawei Hill.
His Majesty acted on impulse.
He forgot Escort Yu in no time
even though she was in high favor.
I hope so.
But who can know His Majesty's mind?
What are you doing?
I'm sorry to have woken Your Majesty.
It was the flickering candlelight.
I was glad to see the candles burning brightly.
Why is that?
I've heard that in a traditional wedding,
they burn a pair of candles until dawn.
So that the newlyweds will accord each other equal respect
and grow old and gray together.
The folk tradition uses red candles
carved with phoenixes.
But I can make do with the plain candles here.
I'm over forty years old.
I will be more than a hundred years old
if you are to grow old and gray with me.
An emperor lives ten thousand years.
Isn't it unfair to make Your Majesty live for
only a hundred years because of me?
You're calculating.
Does Your Majesty think I'm silly for
believing in the red candles?
You have the heart of an innocent child.
It's candid and charming.
In my life,
I had dragon and phoenix candles lit once through the night.
Not twice?
I did not have a nuptial chamber with the current Empress.
Do you really want to grow old and gray with me?
Every girl in this world wishes to grow old with their husband.
I am not out of the ordinary.
But I'm afraid that it's just an extravagant wish.
Do you know that such an "ordinary" feeling
is the most precious in the palace?
I'll treasure your feelings as the jewel in my crown.
I won't let you down.
Don't cry.
I need pen and paper.
For what?
I need to write that down in black and white,
in case Your Majesty reneges on the promise.
You're such a child.
An emperor's words carry weight.
I never deny what I say.
Your Majesty should rest now.
You need to rise early tomorrow.
I’m not sleeping without you.
Peace to My Lady.
- Lingrong.
- Peace to Lady Shen.
You're so early today.
I was going to pay respects to Her Majesty,
but she's feeling unwell today.
So I made my way here.
You have bags under your eyes.
Did you not sleep well last night?
I was talking to Concubine Estime
and lost track of the hours.
Sourire accompanied His Majesty to the Hot Spring Palace last night.
She must have served His Majesty.
Of course, that's expected.
There was probably never a concubine who was sent out of
the Hall of Mental Cultivation like me.
Let bygones be bygones.
You'll do just fine next time.
Next time ...
I'm not as blessed as the two of you.
I'll go congratulate Sourire when she's back.
I bow in respect before Your Majesty.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组🙇‍♀️
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Autumn, help Noble Lady Sourire up.
Yes, Your Majesty.
- I thank Your Majesty.
- My Lady, please rise.
Have a seat.
You've just recovered and returned to the palace.
It must be a lot of trouble for you to follow such etiquette.
But ancestral rule requires that a concubine
must greet the Empress the day after serving His Majesty.
I should have paid my respects the day after my service.
Being in the Changping Palace has caused my delay.
This is my fault.
It is important to observe the rules,
but more so to follow them with flexibility.
You were accompanying His Majesty in the Changping Palace.
I am at peace as long as His Majesty is pleased.
Don't let the rules rule you.
Your Majesty is the Mother of the Nation.
The harem is graced when we see
peace is with Your Majesty.
No wonder His Majesty likes you.
Your words and manners are truly charming.
Your talent and beauty deserve today's favor.
It shouldn't take so long for you to...
Good things don't come easily, but the clouds
have finally dispersed to unveil the bright moon.
You are welcome to my palace anytime you like.
Make yourself at home when you’re here.
Yes.
I really like the fragrance of the fruits in Your Majesty's palace.
It's calming to my mind.
I don't like burning incense, or using rouge and powder.
So I have fresh fruits sent here every day.
It's quite different.
Your Majesty has a unique perspective.
I learned a lot.
Lady Sourire, Her Majesty had intended to visit you
time and again while you were sick.
But the doctor suggested that you stay quarantined.
Her Majesty wasn't able to go.
Her Majesty always had you on her mind.
I thank Your Majesty for your care and concern.
We held the Selection last year for His Majesty
to have more concubines to his liking.
Your priority is to regain good health
and send relief to Heaven by expanding the imperial family.
I will follow every word of Your Majesty's teaching.
I feel a great affinity with you,
and couldn't help getting talkative.
The hour is late.
Autumn, walk Lady Sourire out.
This is wonderful, My Lady.
- My Lady.
- Xiao-Yunzi.
Why aren't you in our palace at this hour?
Allow me to first congratulate My Lady.
This nimble monkey came all the way here to get rewarded.
My Lady won't forget you.
Madam, you misunderstood me.
My Lady, I was instructed to tell you
not to go back right away.
Why is that?
You'll find out later, My Lady.
Please take a walk in the Imperial Garden.
All right.
Your Highness, my stomach is hurting.
Go.
Although Kang Luhai is your servant now,
he still likes to sneak around.
He served Consort Honnête before.
That's why I thought he'd be a reasonable servant.
You have a kind heart, Beauté.
I would never trust a traitor to his old mistress.
The Imperial Garden is so beautiful!
Indeed, the flowers here are different from those elsewhere.
I bow before Noble Lady Sourire.
Peace and grace to My Lady.
It's Kang Luhai.
Kang Luhai.
I'm glad you still remember me, My Lady.
You're working early, sir.
Why aren't you with Concubine Beauté today?
Concubine Beauté and Lady Cao
are paying respects to Her Majesty.
I knew you'd pass through the Imperial Garden on your way back,
so I was waiting here for you, My Lady.
Does Her Highness Concubine Beauté have a message for me?
No, I'm not here because of Concubine Beauté.
I'm here because I wanted to ask you for a favor, My Lady.
Go ahead.
My Lady, I've been wanting to pay respects to you
ever since you were promoted to Noble Lady.
But I couldn't get away from work,
and His Majesty restricted visitors to your palace.
I waited anxiously sticking out my neck,
hoping to see you one day, My Lady.
I can't feel at ease until I pay you my respects.
I prefer the servants to be forthright.
My Lady, if you don't disdain my dull-wittedness,
I will come back to serve you
even if I have to die a thousand deaths.
That's very kind of you.
But does Concubine Beauté know?
Er...
You're already Concubine Beauté's servant.
She might be unhappy if she finds out.
I'm only ranked at Noble Lady.
I cannot make such a request to Concubine Beauté.
Don't worry, My Lady.
You have great blessings from Heaven.
No one in the palace can go against your wish.
All you have to do is ask.
Very well, so you were faking a stomachache
because you saw your former mistress?
Peace and grace to Concubine Beauté.
Peace and grace to Noble Lady Cao.
You shouldn't have. We are at the same rank.
You know her rank is the same as yours,
but she doesn't know her own status.
I understand that His Majesty
had many new servants sent to your palace.
Are there so few to go around
that you would even consider my incompetent eunuch?
Your Highness misunderstood.
Your Highness graced Kang Luhai with your kindness.
He is already your servant.
It wouldn't be proper if I took him away.
Although I'm uneducated about the palace protocol,
I wouldn't dare to make such a mistake.
Lady Sourire is quite well-behaved.
It's not surprising that His Majesty favors you so much.
I can only be left behind in the dust.
It's only because His Majesty pities me for my sickness.
His Majesty's heart holds a place
for Your Highness hundreds of times higher than me.
Stupid eunuch!
Slap yourself for offending Her Highness
so early in the morning.
(My offense deserves death)
Beauté, don't be upset over a eunuch.
Don't let anger affect your health.
"If you give the monkeys three acorns,
they will want four the next time."
It's even worse when the monkeys are castrated.
Nowadays, these lackeys don't have me in their eyes
because they are looking at those hotly favored.
Does he not remember how he was begging me
to dig him out of "the tomb of a living dead?"
Now he wants to be a servant to two masters.
Beauté, I understand you're angry.
But don't waste your breath over a servant.
Lady Sourire, I hope you'll excuse
my harsh words to my servant.
Your Highness is free to punish your servant,
regardless of what you say or do to him.
But many eyes are watching us in the Imperial Garden.
If Your Highness is really upset,
you may as well reprimand him later in your palace.
Enough.
I need to pay respects to the Empress.
I'll spare you for today.
I thank Your Highness.
My Lady, thank you for saving my life.
You are smart.
Concubine Beauté wouldn't have spared me without your intercession.
She might not let you off easily.
Look out for yourself.
Concubine Beauté... They are not happy about you...
My Lady...
Shame on him. What a snob!
Even Concubine Beauté's maid could scold Kang Luhai.
He must be having a hard time working there.
The only way to serve one's master is with loyalty.
We can't trust those who
"obey Qin in the morning and Chu in the evening."
It serves him right.
But Concubine Beauté's words were not nice to hear.
I feel aggrieved for you, My Lady.
I like her straightforward personality.
My Lady, congratulations on
being awarded a pepper-painted room!
This is the greatest honor!
The greatest of the greatest!
Deepest congratulations, My Lady!
Go inside and take a look, My Lady!
Our palace looks stunning!
What is smelling so good?
It's the walls, My Lady.
The walls are fragrant.
By His Majesty's decree early this morning,
we rushed in to decorate your chamber.
I hope you like it, My Lady.
The pepper-painted room is a wedding custom,
wishing for a warm and prolific life.
It can be awarded to the Empress but rarely to the concubines.
Consort Fleur was the only receiver of this honor.
- Congratulations, My Lady.
- Congratulations!
Please go inside, My Lady.
If you would like to take a closer look at your bed.
Is this the custom for a concubine's first-time service?
Thank you, Mr. Huang, for your arrangement.
The custom is one thing, but
His Majesty's well-wishes go deeper underneath.
[copper coins and auspicious fruits
including peanuts, dried dates, and dried longan]
His Majesty took my words to heart.
His Majesty learned about the bed decoration custom
in folk marriage and ordered us to follow suit.
He said if only there was more time before the trip,
this should have been prepared at the Changping Palace.
The time is always right for such a thoughtful surprise.
All right, My Lady should get some rest.
We should take our leave.
Vermilion and Jade will stay to serve her.
Yes.
This is wonderful, My Lady!
Master and Mistress Zhen will be so glad.
It appears that His Majesty holds you
dear to his heart, My Lady.
It's such a relief after all these months.
You're right, but there are many more months to come.
There may be many months,
but your blessings are even more numerous, My Lady.
The other concubines were carried to serve His Majesty.
But your carriage was accompanied by His Majesty.
Don't make fun of me, Meizhuang.
I'm not. I'm happy that you are favored.
But not every concubine would feel the same way.
The rivalries in the palace will never stop rising.
Concubine Beauté is an outspoken person.
Her quick tongue meant no harm.
I'm not worried.
I agree, Concubine Beauté is all right.
But she has Consort Fleur at her back,
who might be alarmed by another pepper-painted room in the palace.
Meizhuang, I never thought His Majesty would treat me so nicely.
Everything went so well and so far beyond my expectations.
Meizhuang, is this even real?
Of course, I see it with my hotly envious eyes.
His Majesty's favor is real.
Concubine Beauté's bitterness is real.
And so are the grudges and rivalries in the harem.
Meizhuang, what should I do?
Endure it.
Endure it?
Even the Empress cannot sway the power of Consort Fleur,
let alone us.
We are new concubines and
cannot hold a candle to her birth or favor.
Competing with her is like striking a stone with eggs.
We'll have to wait and endure.
Your point's well taken.
But will you be angry at me?
I knew this day would come ever since you were selected.
Although His Majesty hasn't summoned me recently,
I feel hopeful as long as you are in favor.
We've been sisters all these years.
I feel envious but won't be angry.
But do you feel upset?
A little bit.
But the palace is never short of favored concubines:
Consort Fleur, yourself, and someone else in the future.
Life is too short to be upset by every one of you.
Another full moon.
I hope my parents are well at home.
Do you miss your family, My Lady?
How can I not when I'm alone and away from home?
But you're not alone here, My Lady.
Lady Sourire and Lady Shen are like sisters to you.
You should visit them more often.
Especially Lady Sourire.
You might even see His Majesty at her palace.
Now that Sourire is rising with the wind,
I would be a nuisance
if I shove myself towards her and His Majesty.
Don't overthink, My Lady.
Lady Sourire is always thoughtful towards you.
She just had two pieces of satin sent to you today.
That was her being generous.
Rifts can grow between the closest friends.
Meizhuang is the closest friend of Sourire,
but she could not sleep well when Sourire served His Majesty.
My Lady, Mr. Xu from Attendance Services.
Peace to Lady Sourire.
Why did you make the trip yourself, sir?
My Lady, His Majesty instructed me to inform you
that you will serve him tonight.
Thank you, sir.
I bid you goodbye.
You just came back to the palace the day before last.
His Majesty can't get enough of you.
Stop it.
Please, My Lady. His Majesty is still reviewing the memorandums.
He'll be here shortly.
Please wait here in the meantime.
Shouldn't I go get changed first?
His Majesty wanted you to wait here, My Lady.
Thank you, Madam.
Your Majesty.
You must be hungry. I got some snacks for you.
Why is there only one serving?
Your Majesty should eat first.
I had some earlier.
Give it a try and see if it suits your taste.
I thank Your Majesty.
It's raw.
If that's what you say.
[The character 生(raw) also means "to have a baby"]
My Lady Sourire is adorable when she is mad.
Your Majesty tricked me.
All right, all right.
It wasn't intended as a trick.
I should have the dumplings served at the Hot Spring Palace.
I heard it's one of the customs in folk weddings.
But we are inhibited by many rules in the palace.
We can't follow all the traditions.
For what I can, I will do everything for you.
Your Majesty treats me so well.
I remember seeing you for the first time,
in the shadows of the apricot flowers.
You looked free and distant,
as if utterly detached from the chaos of the palace.
As if you had left all worldly concerns behind.
I'm flattered by Your Majesty.
The palace abounds with beautiful and talented women.
I am no one compared to them.
Why compare yourself to them?
Zhen Huan is Zhen Huan.
You are perfect the way you are.
She covets my servant when she's just become a Noble Lady.
I can't imagine what she will be like in the future.
You can't blame her for the disloyalty of your own servant.
Instead, when will you learn to control your fiery temper?
You should try to be composed like Lady Cao.
My eyes can't tolerate a single grain of sand.
She'll forget the boundaries when His Majesty continues to favor her.
And the more she does, the sooner His Majesty will stop liking her.
You remember Yu's example.
Lady Sourire isn't bold like her.
She showed a lot of respect for you.
But you lost your temper while she was being courteous.
That is not within the bounds of propriety.
She's just started serving His Majesty.
Just started?
But she has already been granted a pepper-painted room.
Isn't that following Your Highness's example?
And His Majesty has been frequenting the harem this month.
But eight out of ten times was her.
You won't become mute if you don't talk.
Does Your Highness know how to discern a good dog?
The quiet dogs are the ones that bite.
You're a quarter of an hour earlier than yesterday.
I was hoping the night would fall faster.
I just played Go with Your Majesty this afternoon
before I went back for dinner.
"A day of separation feels like three autumns have passed."
The dinner time felt like a year.
Lady Sourire served the night before last,
and again yesterday,
and played Go with His Majesty this afternoon.
Yet again with His Majesty now.
What a minx!
Entangling His Majesty with her witchcraft.
His Majesty likes to be entangled with her.
Her witchcraft is not for everyone.
Yu was arrogant, but nothing like her.
(Register of Attendance)
Wretch!
(name on the doll: Zhen Huan)
You'll die in hell.
Wretch.
Die in hell.
Die in hell, bitch.
I bow in respect before Your Majesty.
I beg Your Majesty's pardon for my lateness.
It's all right. You are young and need more sleep.
I'm grateful for Your Majesty's caring words.
I bow in respect before Your Highnesses.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
You've been busy serving His Majesty recently.
I was hoping to find a chance to have some gifts sent to you.
The lamas made a tribute offering with
consecrated swastika (卍) blankets.
I kept one for you.
It will bring you blessings for having a child soon.
I gratefully thank Your Majesty.
Good for you.
You'll be catching up to Consort Astuce if you have a prince.
Consort Astuce is much blessed.
Unlike the mother of the Fourth Prince.
She couldn't even look at her son before ...
Why did you bring up the Fourth Prince?
You can't gossip about a prince!
This talk ends here in my palace.
His Majesty will be upset if he hears it.
Concubine Beauté, we don't need to remember
the Fourth Prince's mother or anyone who brings bad luck.
Very well, you may leave now.
I'm going to visit the Empress Dowager.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Why would you bring up the Fourth Prince?
Her Majesty is angry now.
Anger hurts one's own health.
Why would you care?
Who is the mother of the Fourth Prince?
Her Majesty is always gracious.
Why was she so upset?
I don't really know, but I remember hearing that
the Fourth Prince's mother was ugly and low-born.
His Majesty disliked her
and thus the Fourth Prince as well.
That's why he keeps the Fourth Prince in the Summer Palace.
If his mother was an ugly lowborn,
why would His Majesty favor her?
Be quiet.
It happened when His Majesty was a lord
and got drunk one day.
The prior emperor furiously reprimanded him about it.
It was a situation fraught with peril when
the nine lords were vying for the throne.
So His Majesty was displeased.
This is taboo in the palace.
Pretend that you know nothing.
Thank you, Meizhuang.
I bow in respect before Consort Fleur.
I bow in respect before Concubine Beauté.
- Rise
- I thank Your Highness.
Lady Sourire was always on time to pay respects to Her Majesty.
What happened today? How unusual.
Your Highnesses are diligent.
I regret my indolence.
I wouldn't say you showed any indolence.
You are tired from serving His Majesty.
Unlike us, idling away our nights and days.
Your Highness has long been in His Majesty's service,
and certainly understands what remarks are within propriety.
I'm new to the palace and my learning is shallow.
I would appreciate any teachings from Your Highness.
If I have misspoke of the palace affairs,
I hope Your Highness won't mind me.
Lady Sourire has been rather busy lately.
Lady Shen has more time to herself.
I wonder if Lady Shen is available
to make a copy of "Analects for Women" for me.
It will remind everyone in the harem of virtuous manners.
I'm honored to obey, Your Highness.
May I ask when Your Highness needs it?
Take your time to make the copy.
I will have it picked up when I need it.
It seems that Lady Shen has got thinner.
Is that because His Majesty hasn't been summoning you?
Your Highness is jesting.
It's just because the heat has spoiled my appetite.
Oh, I see.
I thought it was because you were disturbed
by Lady Sourire's advancement and high favor.
I dare not.
It's not surprising that Lady Sourire
captures His Majesty's eyes with her beauty and intellect.
But unlike the others, you two are like sisters to each other.
When she is having the meat to herself,
how can she forget to share a bowl of the broth?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.